Executive Producer Hou Hsiao Hsien and Hwarng Wern-Ying
出品人候孝tS文英
Editor: Liao Ching-Sun
Ou  廖c松
Starring Shu Qi and Chang Chen
主演  舒淇震
Directed by Hou Hsiao Hsien
а莺蛐①t
THREE TIMES
最好的r光
KAOHSIUNG, 1966
1966高雄
Ma'am...
老娘
You're here!
秀美喔
You came from Xinying?
新I淼男忝溃
Go on in
恚e面坐
I'll be right there when I've made this offering
我金完就M去
Okay
好啊
Need a hand?
要兔幔
No, thanks
不用！不用！
Did you look around?
你有看幔
I'll show you the upstairs
看一看我你去巧
Good
好
May
秀美
Come upstairs for lunch!
等一上沓晕绮
Coming...
好
"Dear Miss Haruko..."
春子小姐
"I'm being bold enough to write to you"
很冒昧@封信o你
"I'm about to do my military service"
我要去兵了
"My folks wrote to me yesterday"
昨天收到家e寄淼男
"They said my call-up notice has arrived"
f我的兵役通知砹
"They're asking me to come home as soon as I can"
要我M快回家
"Time flies..."
r光w逝
"I failed the university entrance exam two years running"
想想自己@赡甏W]考上
"My mother has passed away"
母H去世
"I've no idea what the future holds"
未淼娜兆用Ｃ２豢芍
"I just want to thank you"
跟你f@些，是想xx你
"The days I've spent around here..."
@段在旗後的日子
"...have been my happiest days"
是我最快返r光
"Hope to hear back from you"
衷心盼望能收到你的回音
"Take care"
敬祝安康
"P S. You know that song called 'In Love'?"
P.S.，有一首
"The lyrics go..."
歌~是@拥
"I think of you, I think of you"
思倌悖思倌阊
"It's been three years..."
你我xe三年啦
"But you're always in my dreams"
昨晚的粼硪彩悄愕
"Why do seabirds wake me from my dream?"
港的海B楹未蛐盐颐
"It's because their sad cries..."
啼哭音悲哀
"...pierce my heart"
令人心n
Is Haruko here?
春子在幔
She's gone to Taichung
她去台中了
Taichung?
台中
Do you know where?
台中哪e？
By the railway station
站那e
What's your name?
你叫什N名字？
Your name?
你的名字？
My name is May
我叫秀美
May
秀美
You sank it?
有M幔
Great!
漂亮！
You need to concentrate!
J真一c好不好
I thought I could get this ball over there...
我想打@碰那
...and sink it that way
看不滑M去
No way!
那也差太多了
You haven't sunk a ball for ages!
你很久]M了
So I still lose
我是啊
Right
Π
Never mind
算了
I have to go
我要走了
Go where?
要去哪
I'm starting military service, in Taipei
等一下要去台北兵
Keep the change
不用找了
I'll write to you
信o你
I'll send it here
我寄到@e
"Dear Miss May
秀美小姐
Do you remember me?"
得我幔
"We played one round before I left to do military service"
入伍前跟你撞球的那人
"Time flies"
rg^得w快
"That was three months ago!"
D眼已三月了
"We have non-stop spring rain"
春雨dd
"In our base, they keep playing that song"
此刻，I^正放著披、^四的歌
"It sums up my feelings...
就像我的心情
Hope to see you soon"
期待能再到你
"Stay beautiful!"
祝福，永h美
Have a seat
先坐一坐
Ma'am...
老娘
I should be going
我先走了
Won't you have lunch with us first?
你不吃再走？
I'll miss the train
不用，我要s
You're welcome to come back here anytime
你住不T再回磬福
Thank you
好
Have you worked in Jiayi before?
你是不是在嘉x中正路做^
Yes
是啊
I thought so, I saw you there
我好像看^你
I have to go
我先走了
Hello
你好
Is May here?
秀美在不在
She doesn't work here any more
秀美已不在@e啦
She's gone to Jiayi
她去嘉x_
Jiayi?
嘉x？
Where exactly?
嘉x哪e？
A pool-hall there
嘉x的桌球室
Are you looking for her?
你要找她幔
I can ask our boss
我去湍一下老娘
Ma'am!
老娘
There's a man here looking for May
有人要找秀美
Okay
喔，好
You're looking for May?
你要找秀美？
Yes
Π
She's in Jiayi, at 685, Zhongcheng Road
她F在嘉x中正路685
Zhongcheng Road?
中正路
That's right
是，中正路
GANGSHAN
山
TAINAN
台南
JIAYI
嘉x
Excuse me...
一下
Is there a girl called May here?
秀美有在@幔
She left days ago
秀美十滋烨熬]在@做了
Do you know where she is now?
知道她F在去了哪幔
Sorry, I don't
]她f^
Thanks anyway
xx
One bonus point
加一分
SHUISHANG
水上
XINYING
新I
Excuse me...
一下
This is Number 11, so where's Number 3?
你@e113在哪？
Number 30
30？
That's No. 6... The doctor lives in No. 1
@6，t生那g是1
You can ask there
3不知道，你去那
Anyone in?
有人在幔
Who is it?
l啊？
Who are you looking for?
你要找l？
I'm looking for May
我要找秀美
May?
要找秀美
She's not here, she's in Huwei
她不在家，她去了虎尾
Huwei
虎尾
Who are you?
你是l？
How do you know this address?
你怎N找到@e？
I'm a friend of hers from Kaohsiung
我是她高雄的朋友
She wrote to me
她有信o我
Oh, I see
@
You know where she is?
你知道她F在在哪幔
Yes, she wrote to me the other day
有啦，她有信回
I'll fetch her letter
我去拿o你看
Thank you
xx
See you again!
不，有空再碜啦！
DALIN
大林
DOUNAN
斗南
HUWEl
「虎尾」
You don't have to let me win!
不要我啦！
Long time no see!
很久不
How did you find me here?
你怎N跑磉@？
Your mother told me
你，她跟我f的你在@
It was hard to track you down
真y找
Have you eaten yet?
你吃]有？
What time do you get off?
c下班？
Two hours from now
要2多小r
When are you due back in base?
你什Nr候要回去？
At 9 tomorrow morning
明天一早9c要回部
Have some tea?
喝茶？
Sure
好啊
Thank you
xx
Sit down
坐啊
Cigarette?
要抽幔
Okay
好啊
Hey, spare me a cigarette? Cigarette
你有幔    …
There are no more trains
9：50分…]了
What time you have to be there?
你c要回部？
Nine in the morning
9c
Then we'd better wait at the car-share place
不然我到外面等叫客
DADAOCHENG, 1911
1911大稻埕
When did you arrive?
r上淼
Yesterday... I met Mr Liang on the docks at Keelung
昨日，去基隆港接梁先生
There was a meeting today at the
今日O宴|C芳
Eastern Restaurant, and it was packed
酒DM人
You mean the Mr Liang who fled to Japan...
你是f戊戌年S新失
...when the Reform Movement collapsed?
逃到日本的梁先生
Mr Liang spoke for one hour and wrote out four poems
梁先生演v一小r，亦手四首
and we found them deeply moving
吾人感臃浅
"Our homeland is torn asunder
破碎山河l料得
Our brotherly bond is ever tighter"
Dy兄弟自相H
A TIME FOR FREEDOM
自由
How long will you stay?
@次北上待兹
Five days
五日
I will go with Mr Liang to Taichung, and then come back north
S後陪梁先生下台中，r一起北返
Before the new year, your son had a fever... has he recovered?
年前你小孩l寒幔可痊K了
He is well now, but it took two whole months
已痊K，折磨月
NEXT DAY
翌日
We sincerely wish to resolve the matter of redeeming Ah Mei's contract
H身的事，我有\意解Q
300 silver dollars is a large sum
三百刹皇切的
Is it possible to discuss some more?
可否再⒃
Ah Mei is pregnant by the heir to the Su Tea Plantation
阿妹有身孕，是茶f小_姓K
He is willing to take her as his concubine
娶阿妹殒
What have they decided?
Y果如何
The Su family offers 200 silver dollars
K家出砂
But Madame asks for 300, so they couldn't agree
阿婆要三百，不成
I will make up the difference for them
不足之担我可以
In your articles you have always criticize the keeping of concubines
你多次在蠹撰文，反妾
Aren't you acting against your own principles?
如今可好`背
I do disapprove of keeping concubines...
我反妾
...but in this case, I must assent
然木已成舟
Ah Mei's future must come first
槊妹媒K身有托只能成全
Mr. Chang, your generosity is overwhelming
承蒙老照
Your stay is too short to allow us to show our full gratitude
@次砣ゴ颐Γ不及xx老
Travel safely
路上好走
I will have Ah Mei and her husband thank you in person when you return
月底返斫邪⒚梅D，o老嗑^
SIX DAYS LATER
六日後
I can see that Mr Su is honorable
我看K公子老人
His father is also very understanding, you are blessed.
K老亦明理，是你有福
You will be married tomorrow, and your life will be very different
你明日嫁人，不比在家
Rise early to serve your in-laws
早起送水奉茶侍奉公婆
Always defer to the first wife
c夫人相待要知Y
Never behave willfully.
不可任性
ONE MONTH LATER
一月後
During my travels with Mr Liang
此行陪梁先生
I met many people.
晤多人
It has been very inspiring.
深深受到l
Mr Liang says China will not be ready...
梁先生f三十年
...to help our people secede from Japan...
中^o能力援救
...for another 3 decades.
吾民x日人y治
This is 100 silver dollars.
@是H金一百
Many thanks! Ah Mei is truly fortunate to have found such a good family.
xx，妹妹有福饧薜暮萌思
Madame is seeking a new girl to adopt
近日在找B女
Meanwhile, she asks me to stay here longer
求我多留些r日
She always promised to release me for marriage...
原先答，待阿妹家
...once Ah Mei became a top courtesan herself.
即放我H身嫁人
THE NEXT DAY
翌日
How old are you?
多大了
I am ten.
十q
Good bone structure...
骨骼L得好
A little skinny.
就瘦了些
You are pregnant.
有身孕
Don't overtire yourself.
不能太诶
Today Ah Mei returns
阿妹今日回T
to express her gratitude to you, sir.
特碇xx大
Without your kind intervention, this would not have happened.
不是大相助，哪淼糜薪袢
You leave tomorrow, when will you come again?
明日返家，你何r再
I will assist Mr Liang with his plan for a newspaper.
榱合壬k笫
I may turn up here at any time.
Sr
I have something to ask you...
我有你
Last time you said that you assented in Ah Mei's case...
前次你f
...for the sake of her future.
槊妹媒K身有托，只能成全
Now Madame is asking me to stay here longer.
如今求我，多留些r日
Have you gave a thought about my future?
我想你，可曾想^我的K身
THREE MONTHS LATER THE WUCHANG UPRISING
三月後，武昌起x
"I reached Tokyo a day ago to join Mr Liang"
我日前抵|京，已晤梁公
"We leave for Shanghai tomorrow"
明⒏
"I visited the hall where the treaty ceding Taiwan to Japan was signed"
此行[RP春帆
"Thinking of Mr Liang's poem, I couldn't help shedding tears"
思及梁公，然I下
"Although this place has torn my heart, it is wrenching to leave it.
明知此是心地，亦到S舟首重回
"With all that has passed in these 17 years
十七年中多少事
the tears of the oppressed are not assuaged."
春帆窍峦哀
TAIPEI,2005
2005年台北
Are you okay?
你好吧
A TIME FOR YOUTH
青春
Mother, did you just call me?
，你找我？
I see
我知道了
Are you okay?
你]事吧？
"Born premature"
早a
"Showed up too early..."
太早破出的自我
"High price to pay"
代r是昂F的
"Fractured bones, a hole in the heart"
多骨折，心K破洞
"Epilepsy, almost blind in my right eye"
dB，右眼u盲
"A yen sign branded on my neck"
「胸口烙」￥
"Name your price! I want to sell my soul..."
_r吧！我要u`魂
"No past, no future, just a hungry present"
]有^去，恚只有|I的F在…
Please open your eyes
_你的p眼
Open your ears
打_你的耳朵
Check you brain
敲敲你的X袋
To realize what you want
t解你想要什N
To realize who you are
t解你是l
No one can decide how you feel
]有人能Q定你怎N想
Don't be afraid to
不要怕
Liberate deep inside your mind
解放你刃纳钐
The color which you've seen
你所^的色
The shape which you're in
你所在的形
May reveal the secret
可能透露了秘密
You've never known before
你以前牟恢道
So celebrate when you're honest to yourself
所以c祝吧，你\面ψ约
So celebrate when you no need to disregard how you feel
所以c祝吧 你不需要忽略你的感X
So celebrate when you feel different from mine
你的感受和我不同的r候
Let's celebrate when we no need to tell lie and hide
我c祝吧 我不需要fe和[藏
"I suffer from epilepsy"
「我是dBY患者」
"Please do not call an ambulance"
「不要叫救o」
"Please move me to a safe, warm place"
「把我移到安全嘏的角落」
"Taipei Medical University Hospital"
「台北tW院附O大W」
Piss off!
走
Come home
回去啦
Don't bug me!
干麻啦！
I need napkins
我要巾
Pass me some napkins
o我巾
Thanks
xx
Why didn't you take my calls?
你怎N都不接？
I kept ringing, you never picked up
我打o你都不接
Even if you were sleeping, you could have called back
你在睡X你也可以打o我啊
I was sleeping
在睡X啊
Why didn't you call me to say so?
可是你可以打跟我f
I told you I was tired
跟你f我很累
Then why did you switch off your phone after my call?
槭颤N我打你    之後你就PC？
I told you, I had a fit
我跟你v我放完了
But right after you texted me
可是你魍暧息o我
you switched off your phone
我打o你就是PC
I went to sleep right away
之後我就睡了
You could still have called me
可是你可以打o我
Couldn't you hear your phone?
而且我打o你你]有到幔
Couldn't you?
你都]有到幔
I left it in vibration mode
我_震
Don't be angry
不要生饬撕貌缓茫
If you were me, what would you think?
可是如果今天是你怎想？
I'll wait for you when you finish, okay?
我等你收工回家好不好？
TEXT MESSAGE
收到文字息
"Can't sleep, miss you, you left your epilepsy card at my place"
「睡不著，想你，你的dB卡掉在我家」
"Developed the photos, will show you tomorrow"
「照片洗好了，明天交o你」
I burn my hand every time I light a candle with this lighter.
每次用@打火CcT，都C到手
My thumb hurts.
大拇指好痛
It's almost run out.
如果再不能用了
I can hardly light this one.
根本]k法c
Pass that one to me.
臀夷靡幌履
Thanks.
x啦
We'll light this one later.
那等一下再放
And that one.
有那
That one too.
那的都要c
Has water gone inside?
@些干麻，泡到水是不是
You hear that funny sound?
你到啪差啪差的音
The wick is wet.
水跑M去了
Let's buy some new ones tomorrow.
明天在I些新的
There are two left.
有另外
The water is dirty.
@水都v了
Can you change it later?
等一下你去Q一下
Is it because of the candle wax?
是因槟油幔
I can't even light them
根本c不著
Shall I put some fragrant oils in the bath?
泡澡用伊m跟鼠尾草好幔
Okay
好
Let's bathe together.
那一起洗喔
I'll take silence as a 'Yes'
你不回答我就你答我
Okay
好
I'll go get clothes
那我去拿衣服
"The pictures taken before
以前拍的照片
"With smiling gray eyes
灰色眼睛的微笑
"May rest, such cruel sound
也S停止，如此酷的音
Jing! It's ready, hurry up!
靖，好啦！快c
"It's still vivid, like a bird"
仍栩栩如生，好像一bB一
Jing...
靖！
You're still awake?
你]睡？
Grandma made some chicken soup
阿婆有蹼u
I'll get some for you?
我端上斫o你喝？
Jing!
靖！
Grandma made some chicken soup
阿婆有蹼u
I'll get some for you?
我端上斫o你喝？
Okay
好
Sorry, I'm late
Σ黄硗砹
I called you just now
我打^你
But you didn't answer
但你]有接
The photos.
相片
Go to your place.
去你家
Jing?
靖？
"One missed call"
未接黼
"Connecting..."
BY中
You must have gone out before 12:45.
你在12：45以前出T的
You left your cell phone here.
你留下了手C
I think you did it on purpose.
我想你是故意的吧
To make me think you had...
故意我知道你只在附近
just stepped out for a minute.
只出去一下
Your last missed call was at 12.45.
你手C最後未接是12：45
So you'd have gone by then.
我想你是在那之前出T的
Now it's 3:33.
F在已3：33
You've been out for over 3 hours.
你出去超^3小r
You knew I'd wake up at 4.
你知道我4c醒
I don't want to hear any more of your lies.
我不想再你的e言
I'm fed up with waiting for you.
不想再等你了
You keep pushing me.
你都@颖莆
You know that I love you more than you love me.
你知道我勰惚饶畚叶
You'll regret this
你後悔的
I will kill myself just like Olika.
我死的，就像香
"I think you did it on purpose"
我想你是故意的吧
"Your last missed call was at 12:45"
未接是12：45
"You've been out for over 3 hours"
你出去超^3小r
"I don't want to hear anymore of your lies"
我不想再你的e言
"I'm fed up with waiting for you"
不想再等你了
"You keep pushing me"
你都@颖莆
"You know that I love you more than you love me"
你知道我勰惚饶畚叶
"You'll regret this"
你後悔的
"I will kill myself just like Olika"
「我死的，就像香」